<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Prynne the Member reconciled to Prynne the barrester. Or An ansvver to a scandalous pamphlet, intituled, Prynne against Prynne. Wherein is a cleare demonstration, that William Prynne, utter barrester of Lincolnes Inne, in his soveraigne power of parliaments and kingdomes, is of the same judgement with, and no wayes contradictory to William Prynne Esquire, a Member of the House of Commons in his memento. Wherein the unlawfullnesse of the proceedings against the King, and altering the present government is manifested out of his former writings and all cavils and calumnies of this scandalous pamphleteer fully answered. / By William Prynne Esquire, barrester at law, and a Member of the House of Commons.</title>
            <author>Prynne, William, 1600-1669.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1649</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A91250</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing P4043</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E558_5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R203281</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99863280</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99863280</idno>
            <idno type="VID">115470</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A91250)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 115470)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 86:E558[5])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Prynne the Member reconciled to Prynne the barrester. Or An ansvver to a scandalous pamphlet, intituled, Prynne against Prynne. Wherein is a cleare demonstration, that William Prynne, utter barrester of Lincolnes Inne, in his soveraigne power of parliaments and kingdomes, is of the same judgement with, and no wayes contradictory to William Prynne Esquire, a Member of the House of Commons in his memento. Wherein the unlawfullnesse of the proceedings against the King, and altering the present government is manifested out of his former writings and all cavils and calumnies of this scandalous pamphleteer fully answered. / By William Prynne Esquire, barrester at law, and a Member of the House of Commons.</title>
                  <author>Prynne, William, 1600-1669.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>26, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>[s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>Printed anno Dom. 1649.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to "Prynne against Prinn", which Prynne attributes to Col. William Purefoy or possibly to George Abbot (p. 26).</note>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "4th June ".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Purefoy, William, 1580?-1659. --  Prynn against Prinn.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1642-1649 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2007-02</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2007-03</date>
            <label>Aptara</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:115470:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>PRYNNE
The MEMBER reconciled to
PRYNNE
The <hi>BARRESTER.</hi> OR
An Anſwer to a Scandalous
Pamphlet, Intituled,
PRYNNE againſt PRYNNE. Wherein is a cleare demonſtration, That <hi>William
Prynne,</hi> Vtter Barreſter of <hi>Lincolnes Inne,</hi> in his
<hi>Soveraigne Power of Parliaments and Kingdomes,</hi> is of
the ſame Judgement with, and no wayes contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dictory
to <hi>William Prynne</hi> Eſquire, A Member of the
<hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> in his MEMENTO. Wherein the unlawfullneſſe of the Proceedings againſt
the King, and altering the preſent Government is manifeſted out
of his former writings and all cavils and calumnies of this
ſcandalous <hi>Pamphleteer</hi> fully Anſwered.</p>
            <p>By <hi>William Prynne</hi> Eſquire, Barreſter at Law, and a
<hi>Member of the</hi> Houſe of Commons.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Tit. 1. 12. 13.</bibl>
               <p>One of themſelves, even a Prophet of their owne, ſaid; The Creti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans
ARE ALWAYES LYARS, evill beasts, ſlow Bellies:
This witneſſe is true: wherefore rebuke them ſharply, that they
may be ſound in the faith.</p>
            </q>
            <p>LONDON Printed <hi>Anno Dom.</hi> 1649.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:115470:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:115470:2"/>
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Curteous Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>MEeting this morning with a printed <hi>Pamphlet</hi> inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled
<hi>Prynne</hi> againſt <hi>Prynne;</hi> Or the anſweer of
<hi>William Prynne,</hi> Vtter-Barreſter of <hi>Lincolnes Inne;</hi>
to a <hi>pamphlet,</hi> lately publiſhed by <hi>william Prynne</hi> Eſq;
a <hi>Member</hi> of the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> intituled, <hi>a
breif Memento to the preſent unparliamentary</hi> I <hi>un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to;</hi>
touching their preſent intentions and proceedings to De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe
and Execute <hi>CHALES STEVVARD,</hi> their lawfull Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne:
with an <hi>Imprimatur</hi> of <hi>Theodore Iennings,
Jan.</hi> 25. 1648. prefixed to it: written (as I am credibly
informed) by a <hi>Colonell, a Member</hi> of the <hi>Commons
Houſe,</hi> and one of his <hi>Majeſties</hi> preſent <hi>Judges,</hi> to repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent
and render me an <hi>Apoſtate,</hi> and <hi>turne-coate</hi> to the
world (like himſelfe) and to gaine ſome colour for this unjuſt
and <hi>illegall proceedings,</hi> (if poſsible) from my <hi>writings,</hi>
who ever from my Soule abominated and declared againſt
them as <hi>Jeſuiticall</hi> and <hi>Treaſonable</hi> in all my writings;
<hi>I</hi> held it my duty to returne this ſhort and ſpeedy <hi>Anſwer</hi>
thereunto; both to vindicate my wounded <hi>reputation,</hi> againſt
all imputations of <hi>inconſtancy,</hi> and mutability in my <hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples,</hi>
or <hi>actions,</hi> which have been alwayes loyall, uniform,
ayming onely at the <hi>Common-good,</hi> not <hi>vertiginous,</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:115470:3"/>
mutable; <hi>perfidious,</hi> and <hi>ſelfiſh,</hi> as his and his <hi>Confede<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rates</hi>
appeare to all men. It is Gods owne glory to be,<note n="a" place="margin">Mal. 3. 6.</note>
               <hi>unchangeable,</hi>
               <note n="b" place="margin">Iam, 1. 17.</note> 
               <hi>unvariable,</hi> and <hi>without ſhadow
of turning:</hi>
               <note n="c" place="margin">Heb. 13. 8.</note> 
               <hi>yeſterday, to day, and the ſame for
ever.</hi>
               <note n="d" place="margin">Cam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, Eli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zabeth, Speed, <hi>&amp;</hi> Hollin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed.</note> SEMPER EADEM, was Qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>een <hi>Elizabeths</hi>
Motto: and <hi>Semper idem,</hi> ſhall be (through Gods aſsiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance)
mine: who as I am commanded by God himſelfe, <hi>to
be</hi>
               <note n="e" place="margin">1 Cor 15. 58.</note> 
               <hi>alwayes ſtedfaſt, unmoveable,</hi> and<note n="f" place="margin">Prov. 24<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 21.</note> 
               <hi>not to
meddle</hi> (or confederate) <hi>with thoſe who are given to
change;</hi> So, <hi>I</hi> trust, to manifeſt my ſelfe in this enſuing
<hi>Tract,</hi> (in deſpite of calumny) to be still <hi>the ſame I was</hi>
heretofore, both to the <hi>Kings</hi> and <hi>Kingdomes</hi> true and
reall intereſt, which now lye both at <hi>Stake,</hi> likely to be <hi>ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dily
and irrecoverably</hi> loſt by ſome <hi>falſe</hi> rooking <hi>Game<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters,</hi>
who play badly for themſelves. Which is the feare and
apprehenſion of their and his poore <hi>Countries</hi> freind, and
<hi>wel-wiſher,</hi> (for which he is once more like to become a
<hi>Martyr.)</hi>
            </p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>January 29 <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>648.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>William Prynne</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:115470:3"/>
            <head>PRYNNE the Member, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conciled
to PRYNNE the
BARRESTER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Ad the Compi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>er of the late <hi>abſurd Pamphlet,</hi> inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuled
<hi>Prynne againſt Prynne,</hi> as many <hi>guts</hi> in his
<hi>Braines</hi> as he hath in his Belly or as much <hi>Honeſty</hi>
&amp; <hi>Sincerity</hi> in his <hi>Head</hi> &amp; <hi>Heart,</hi> as he hath <hi>diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty</hi>
&amp; inſincerity in both, he could <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ot have been
ſo <hi>irrationall</hi> or <hi>diſhoneſt,</hi> as to have publiſhed ſuch
a peece of <hi>Folly</hi> and <hi>Non-ſence</hi> as this, inſtead of anſwering the <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento;</hi>
which (though a Right worſhipfull <hi>Colonell</hi> and a <hi>Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi>
too) yet he dares not encounter; his <hi>braines</hi> being all ſunke
into his <hi>guts;</hi> &amp; his <hi>Pen</hi> as blunt as his <hi>ſword,</hi> that never yet ſlew nor
wounded one <hi>Cavalier,</hi> though he hath <hi>gained</hi> and <hi>received</hi> ſome
thouſand of pounds for his <hi>Grand Services</hi> in theſe late <hi>Warres.</hi>
When this <hi>Great Champion</hi> dare op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nly appeare in the field <hi>againſt</hi>
any thing I have written, with his name thereto affixed, (of which
it ſeemes he is aſhamed) I dare aſſure him, <hi>William Prynne,</hi> the
<hi>Barreſter,</hi> or <hi>William Prynne</hi> the <hi>Member;</hi> will hand to hand en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counter.
<hi>W. P.</hi> the <hi>Colonel,</hi> or <hi>W. P.</hi> the <hi>Burgeſſe</hi> of <hi>W.</hi> though
a <hi>Gyant</hi> in bulke, but a <hi>Pigmy</hi> in moſt things elſe. But to come brief<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
to the matter.</p>
            <p>It is very true, which he relates, <hi>pag.</hi> 1. That <hi>William Prynne</hi>
Eſquire a Member of the <hi>Houſe of Commons,</hi> did in his <hi>Briefe Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento</hi>
endeavour to <hi>diſwade the reſt of the Members ſitting in Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
from acting or proceeding againſt the King.</hi> And had they
been ſo provident, wiſe and <hi>loyall,</hi> as to have given an eare to his
ſeaſonable &amp; timely adviſe, they had never plunged themſelves &amp; the
<hi>Kingdome</hi> into ſuch difficulties and <hi>confuſions</hi> as now they have done
by their unjuſt and illegall tryall and condemnation of the King, to
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:115470:4"/>
               <hi>have His head ſevered from his ſhoulders,</hi> by a <hi>New erected high
Court of Iuſtice;</hi> without authority, law, juſtice, or any legall or ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diciall
proceedings: for which they found no warrant nor preſident
in <hi>William Prynne</hi> the <hi>Barreſter</hi> his <hi>Soverain Power of Parliaments
&amp; Kingdomes;</hi> but many arguments againſt and dehortations from it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt, The very Title of his Booke (had the</hi> purblinde Pamphle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
<hi>peruſed it) might have deterred him and his fellow-members
from ſuch a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſuiticall and popiſh proceeding, to the eternall infamy
and ſcandall of our Religion: it is this. <hi>The treachery and diſloy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty
of Papiſts to their Soveraignes</hi> in Doctrine and <hi>Practiſe,</hi>
               </hi>
together with the firſt part of the Soveraigne power of Parliaments
and Kingdomes. Wherein the <hi>Traiterous Antimonarchicall Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrines,
practiſes</hi> and attempts <hi>of Papiſts</hi> upon the <hi>Perſons, Crowns</hi>
Prerogatives of their <hi>Soveraignes:</hi> with the dangerous deſignes,
affests and conſequences, of their preſent illegal arming, and acceſſe to
the Kings perſon, by meanes of evil Councellors, are briefly diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red.
The Iuriſdiction, Power, priviledges claimed, exerciſed by our
<hi>popiſh Parliaments,</hi> Prelates, Lords and Commons, in former ages,
exactly paralleld with thoſe now claimed by <hi>the Lords and Com<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>mons</hi>
in this preſent Parliament: which are manifeſted to be <hi>far more
loyall, dutifull,</hi> moderate; more conſiſtant with, leſſe invaſive <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>,
and destructive to the pretended Soveraigne power and Prerogative
of the King, then thoſe in former ages. And the High Court of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
proved by pregnant Reaſons and Authorities; to be the moſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
ſoveraigne power of all other in this Kingdome, &amp;c. <hi>By <hi>William
Prynne,</hi>
               </hi> Utter-Barreſter of Lincolnes Inne, <hi>with this Licenſe of
the Commons Houſe affixed to it. It is this ſecond day of</hi> May 1643.
Ordered by the Committee <hi>of the Houſe of Commons in Parliament</hi>
for printing: that this Booke <hi>intituled <hi>the Treachery and diſloyal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>y
of papiſts to their Soveraigns</hi> &amp;c.</hi> be printed, <hi>by</hi> Michael Sparke
<hi>Seino<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> Iohn White: <hi>Whence the Argument ſtands thus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Maſter <hi>Prynne</hi> the Barreſter, though he mainteined the High
Court of Parliament to be the moſt Soveraigne Power of all others
in this Kingdome; in his <hi>Soveraigne Power of Parliaments:</hi> yet he
and the Committee of the Commons Houſe which authotized it,
doth in the very Title of that Booke, in expreſſe termes condemne
the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>popiſh Parliaments,</hi> of <hi>Treachery</hi> and <hi>Diſloyalty to
their Soveraignes, both in Doctrine and practiſe,</hi> and of <hi>Trayterous
Antimonarchiall <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ractiſes and attempts upon the Perſons, Crownes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:115470:4"/>
and Prerogatives of their Kings, in depoſing and murdering them.
And manifeſts the Iuriſdiction, Power and priviledges claimed</hi> b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
the <hi>Lords and Commons</hi> (not the Commons alone without the Lords,
or the tenth part of the Commons under the Armies force, whiles
the reſt are impriſoned and ſecluded by them) <hi>to be farre more loyall,
dutifull and moderate then thoſe claimed and exerciſed by our popi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
Parliaments, Prelates, Lords and Commons: Ergo,</hi> he refu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>es <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liam,
Prynne</hi> a Member of the Houſe of Commons: in his <hi>breife Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento
to the preſent unparliamentary Iunto,</hi> wherein he diſwades
them from their preſent diſlo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>all proceedings to depoſe and execute
<hi>Charles Stewad</hi> their lawfull King; as being a <hi>Ieſuiticall and popiſh
practiſe,</hi> contrary to the practiſe and principles of all proteſtant Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments;
and the manifold Petitions, <hi>Remonſtrances, Declarations,
Proteſtations, Solemne Leagues, Covenants</hi> and Engagement of this
preſent Parliament. Whether <hi>Prynne</hi> be againſt <hi>Prynne</hi> in this, and
whether <hi>Prynne</hi> the Barreſter &amp; <hi>Member,</hi> be not both unanimous a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
their proceedings herein, let the world, &amp; this ignorant miſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken
Pamphleter now judge.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> the <hi>Barreſter,</hi> in the foure firſt Pages of the
<hi>firſt Part</hi> of his <hi>Soveraigne Power of Parliaments,</hi> in as poſitive and
earneſt manner as can be, <hi>condemnes and cenſures the Ieſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>its and Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſts
doctrines and practiſes, in depoſing</hi> and murdering Kings and
Princes, as <hi>treaſonable, damnable, wicked and hereticall:</hi> and parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cularly,
chargeth them for attempting <hi>to deſtroy and murder Hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
Majesty and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſterity,</hi> as well as Queene <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and King
<hi>Iames,</hi> alleaging many <hi>proteſtant Writers</hi> of our owne Church, as
Doctour <hi>Iohn Whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> Biſhop <hi>Iewel,</hi> Biſhop <hi>Bilſon,</hi> and others, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning
them for this their <hi>doctrine and practiſe, which can stand
neither with peace nor piety. Ergo,</hi> Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> the <hi>Member,</hi> who
doth the very ſame in his <hi>Memento;</hi> are both accorded, and not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
one another, but both againſt this <hi>Pamphleters,</hi> and his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>federares,
<hi>Ieſuiticall, popiſh Aſſertions,</hi> and <hi>practiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Adde hereunto, that Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> the Barreſtet, not onely in his
<hi>Truth triumphing over falſhood, antiquity over novelty,</hi> printed by
Order of the Commons Houſe 1644. and in his <hi>ſword of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
Magiſtracy ſupported</hi> Anno 1646. hath aſſerted <hi>the Power and
Prerogative of Chriſtian Princes and Kings,</hi> as much as <hi>any man in
Eccleſiaſticall matters;</hi> but in his <hi>third part of the Soveraign pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
of Parliaments</hi> and Kingdomes, p. 62<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 63 determines thus. <hi>Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:115470:5"/>
Neither is this any parcell of the Controverſy</hi> (between the
King and Parliament.) Whether Subjects may <hi>lay violent hands up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
the perſons of their Princes; wittingly or willingly, <hi>To deprive
them, of their Lives, or Liberties:</hi> eſpecially <hi>In cold blood,</hi>
when they do not actually, nor perſonally</hi> aſſault <hi>their lives or chaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyes,
or for any publike miſdemeanours,</hi> without a precedent ſentence
of <hi>impriſonment or death againſt them given judicially by <hi>the whole
State or Realme,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">As in ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>me elections and Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> times.</note> * <hi>where they have ſuch authority to araigne or
condemne them, for all unan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>mouſly diſclaime, yea abominate ſuch
trayterous practiſes, and Ieſuiticall poſitions, as execrable and
unchriſtian.</hi> Fourthly,</hi> Neither is this <hi>the thing in difference, as moſt
miſtake</hi> it: <hi>Whether the Parliament may lawfully raiſe an Army,
to goe</hi> immediately and directly againſt <hi>the perſon of the King,</hi> to
apprehend, or <hi>offer violence to Him, much leſſe intentionally to
deſtroy Him, <hi>or to reſist his owne Perſonall attempts against them,</hi>
               </hi>
even to <hi>the hazard of his life.</hi> For<note n="*" place="margin">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> Col<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection of all Remon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrances. &amp;c<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> the <hi>Parliament</hi> and <hi>their Army
too, <hi>have in ſundry</hi>
               </hi> Remonſtrances, Declarations, Proteſtations,
and petitions <hi>renounced any ſuch intention or deſigne at all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>for
which there is no colour to charge them:</hi>
               </hi> when <hi>neither the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
nor their forces</hi> in <hi>this their resiſtance, <hi>have the leaſt thought
at all to offer any violence to the Kings owne perſon,</hi> or to oppoſe</hi>
his <hi>legall juſt ſoveraigne authority.</hi> The very words and languages
of Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> the Member in his <hi>Memento,</hi> who is ſtill conſonant to
himſelfe in both: And <hi>p.</hi> 92. to 98. he addes, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> proves,<note n="*" place="margin">Cook. 7. Report. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> caſe of f. 11<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> P<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>il<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>. A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ch. de <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Vinda<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>i. c. 17<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> 
               <hi>That
hereditary Kings are Kings before their <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> coronation,
which is but a ceremony:</hi> That it is <hi>falſe</hi> and <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>to affirme, that
Heredit<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ry Kings before their Coronations,</hi>
               </hi> ti<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>they are anoynted,
are not ſacred, nor <hi>exempt from violence.</hi> That</hi> Saules <hi>perſon was
ſacred, exempt from his Subjects violence, not becauſe he was anoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted,
as if that onely did priviledge him: but <hi>becauſe he was a King</hi>
appoynted by the Lord himſelfe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> That theſe texts and ſpeeches of</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,
1 <hi>Sam. 24. 6. 10. c. 26 v. 21. 23. 2 Sam.</hi> 1. 12. 16. The Lord for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bid
that I ſhould doe this thing unto my Maſter the Lords anointed,
to ſtretch forth my hand againſt him, ſeeing he is the Lords anointed.
I will not put forth my hand againſt my Lord, for he is the Lords a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nointed;
And <hi>David</hi> ſaid to <hi>Abiſhai,</hi> (when he would have ſlaine
<hi>Saul)</hi> Deſtroy him not, for who can ſtretch forth his hand againſt the
Lords anointed, and be guiltleſſe? The Lord forbid, that I ſhould
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:115470:5"/>
ſtretch forth my hand againſt the Lords anointed. For waſt thou not
afraid to ſtretch forth thy hand againſt the Lords anointed? Thy
blood ſhall be upon thy head, for thy mouth hath teſtified, that thou
haſt ſl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ine the Lords anointed, &amp;c. Prove, That <hi>Subiects ought
not wilfully or purpoſely to murder or offer violence to the Perſon
of their Kings, eſpecially in cold blood, <hi>when they doe not actually
aſſault them. That David and his men might not with ſafe conſcience,
ſtretch forth their hands,</hi>
               </hi> nor <hi>riſe up against their Soveraigne
King</hi> Saul, <hi>to aſſault or kill him</hi> thus <hi>in cold blood, without any aſſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ault
or preſent provocaetion: which had been <hi>treachery and unpiety</hi>
in a Sonne in Law, a ſervant, <hi>a ſubiect,</hi> a ſucceſſor, who ſlew the</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malekite,
<hi>that came and brought him tidings of</hi> Sauls <hi>death,</hi> (to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether
with his Crown and bracelet) inſtead of giving him a reward,
(a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> he likewiſe<note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> put <hi>Baanah</hi> and <hi>Richab</hi> to death <hi>as Traytors,</hi> who
having murdered King <hi>Iſhboſheth,</hi> though his enemy, and corrivall
inſtead of rewarding them, and hanged up their hands and feet) <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe
he reported himſelfe had ſlaine him, to gain a reward from</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid:
<hi>which concludes that it was not lawfull for any of</hi> Sauls <hi>own men
to ſlay him,</hi> (no not in an exigent) <hi>by his owne command.</hi> Aud he con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes.
<hi>That the evaſion of Doctor</hi> Ferne: <hi>That</hi> Davids <hi>dem<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>nor
&amp;c.</hi> was <hi>extraordinary,</hi> derogating exceedingly from <hi>the perſonall
ſafety of Princes; <hi>yea, and</hi> expoſing them to ſuch perils, <hi>as they
have cauſe to con the Doctor ſmall thankes</hi>
               </hi> for <hi>ſuch <hi>a bad</hi> invention,
<hi>I ſhall reiect it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
               </hi> as the extraordinary fancy of the Doctour and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<hi>Lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>aliſts</hi> (or Jeſuiſts) <hi>void both <hi>of truth</hi>
               </hi> and <hi>loyalty<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> Now
what Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> the <hi>Member</hi> could have written more in point
of law and conſcience poſitively and directly againſt the unlawfulnes
and diſloyalty of the <hi>Junctoes,</hi> and their <hi>High Courts</hi> arraigning
and <hi>putting the King to death,</hi> and that in cold <hi>blood</hi> (contrary to
their faith, <hi>Oaths, Engagements,</hi> even after the <hi>Treaty,</hi> and above
two yeares after his firſt impriſonment) then what he hath thus
written and printed as a <hi>Barreſter,</hi> (by the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> own
<hi>Order and approbation, dated May the</hi> 8. 1643. prefixed to <hi>the
third part,)</hi> or whether theſe paſſages doe not moſt fully and
punctually concurre with what he hath publiſhed and aſſerted in his
<hi>MEMENTO,</hi> to the eternall reproach and ſhame of this <hi>ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litions
Impoſtor</hi> and perverter of his words and opinion, let all
ſober and unb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>aſſed men reſolve. And if theſe paſſages be not ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent,
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:115470:6"/>
his <hi>Hiſtriomaſtix</hi> printed Anno 1633. <hi>p.</hi> 516, to 520. 825.
826. 943. with his anſwer to the Bill concerning it, in the <hi>Star-Chamber,</hi>
wherein he did upon his oath, <hi>condemne and abhor</hi> from
<hi>his heart, the popiſh Doctrine and practiſe, of murdering and depoſing
Kings, as contrary to the Oathes of Supremacy and Allegiance, which
he had taken as a Barrester. His Epiſtle before his Quench-coal</hi> Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed.
<hi>Anno 1638. wherein he interminis condemnes this Popiſh
and Jeſuiticall doctrine and practiſe, as faction, rebellion</hi> and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon.
<hi>His pleaſant Purge for a Romane Catholick,</hi> p. 104. <hi>to</hi> 112. prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted
1642. where (as an <hi>Vtter-Barreſter)</hi> he <hi>particularly refutes and
cenſures the Popes and Jeſuits doctrine and practiſe of killing or dep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing
Kings, and abſolving Subjects from their Oathes and Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,</hi>
anſwering all their arguments and texts to prove it. And <hi>the
Antipathy of the Engliſh Lordly Prelacy,</hi> both <hi>to Regall verity and
Civil unity: or, an hiſtoricall Collection of the ſeverall <hi>execrable
Treaſons. Conſpiracies, Rebellions,</hi> ſeditions, State ſchiſmes,
Contuma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ies, Oppreſſions,</hi> and <hi>Antimonarchicall practiſes,</hi> of our
<hi>Engliſh, Britiſh, French, Scottiſh</hi> and <hi>Iriſh Lordly Prelates</hi> againſt
<hi>our Kings, Kingdomes &amp;c.</hi> publiſhed by him as <hi>an Utter-Barre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi>
and dedicated to the <hi>Parliament, Anno</hi> 1641. will abun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dantly
abſolve him from this ſcandalous <hi>ſcriblers</hi> miſrepreſentation
of his <hi>loyalty,</hi> and falſe ſurmiſes <hi>contrariety</hi> of his writings, as a
Barreſter and Member, which have been alwayes <hi>loyall</hi> and <hi>harmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nious</hi>
againſt killing or depoſing of Kings, ayming at nothing but the
<hi>Honor, peace</hi> and <hi>happi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eſſe</hi> both of the <hi>King, Kingdome, Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
Church,</hi> without any private or ſiniſter ends whatſoever,
as all impartiall PERVSERS of them cannot but acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly, Mr.</hi> Prynne <hi>the</hi> Barreſter, <hi>in the ſame firſt Part,</hi> page 7
<hi>aſſerts and proves.</hi> That popiſh Parliaments, Peeres and Prelates,
<hi>have</hi> heretofore challenged and exerciſed a greater Iuriſdiction over
their Kings, then this Parliament, or <hi>any other <hi>ſince</hi>
               </hi> the embracing
of the Proteſtant Religion <hi>ever claimed,</hi> and doe in a great meaſure
<hi>diſclaime. <hi>For proofe whereof he ſhewed,</hi>
               </hi> That they had challenged
a juſt and legall Power, <hi>(as they deemed it)</hi> to depoſe their Kings:
<hi>produceth preſidents to prove it, and among others the preſidents
of King</hi> Edward <hi>the 2d. and</hi> Richard <hi>the 2d. who were firſt enforced
to</hi> reſigne their Crownes, <hi>and after that, (not arraigned and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:115470:6"/>
to loſe their heads, in a High Court of Iuſtice, as now)</hi> had
a ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tence of depoſition drawne up againſt them, <hi>but were to</hi> be ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourably
treated and maintained all their lives, page 7. 8. 78. to 80.
<hi>and p. 9. he writes.</hi> That our popiſh Parliaments, Peeres and Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates
have oft tranſlated the Crowne from the right Heires, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led
it on others who had no right nor title to it, <hi>producing examples
to prove it: In the cloſe whereof he writes thus.</hi> Such a tranſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent
power and juriſdiction as this, to diſinherit the right Heire, and
to transferre the Crowne to whom they thought meeteſt, <hi>Neither
this preſent, nor any other proteſtant Parliaments, Peeres or
Subiects ever exerciſed, <hi>though</hi>
               </hi> popiſh Parliaments, Lords &amp; Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
have thus frequently done it. <hi>And</hi> p. 86. <hi>he addes.</hi> True it is,
<hi>Our <hi>proteſtant Parliaments never challenged nor exerciſed ſuch
Juriſdiction,</hi> and</hi> I preſume <hi>they will not do it. <hi>And good reaſon
had he thus to write, becauſe the</hi>
               </hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">E<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>act C<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>llecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. p. 657<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 658.</note> Lords and Commons in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,
in their Anſwer to his Majeſties Declaration, <hi>after his late</hi>
victory againſt the Rebels <hi>on Sunday the 23. of</hi> October 1642. <hi>had
but a few moneths before made this</hi> Proteſtation <hi>to all the world</hi>
concerning the allegations, <hi>That the Army raiſed by the Parliament,
is <hi>to murder and depoſe the King.</hi>
               </hi> We hoped the contrivers of that
Declaration, or any that profeſſed the name of a Chriſtian could
not have ſo little charity, as to raiſe <hi>ſuch a ſcandall:</hi> eſpecially, when
they muſt needs know the Proteſtation taken by every Member of
both Houſes, whereby they promiſe in the preſence of Almighty God
<hi>to defend his Maieſties Perſon.</hi> The promiſe and proteſtation made
by the Members of both Houſes upon the nomination of the Earle of
<hi>Eſſex</hi> to be Generall, and to live and dye with him, wherein is ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſed:
That this Army was raiſed for <hi>Defence of the Kings
perſon,</hi> our often earneſt and humble addreſſes to his Majeſty to
leave that deſperate and dangerous Army, wherewith he is now en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compaſſed,
raiſed and upheld to the hazard if his owne, and the
Kingdomes ruine. And to come in perſon to his Parliament, where
he ſhould be ſure to remaine in honour and ſafety. And our humble
Petition directed to be preſented to him by the hands of the Earle of
<hi>Eſſex,</hi> before any blow given, to remove his Royall Perſon from that
Army, a requeſt inconſiſtant with any purpoſe to offer the leaſt vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence
to his perſon, which hath and <hi>ever ſhall be deare unto us.</hi>
And concerning the Imputation laid to our charge, of our raiſing this
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:115470:7"/>
Army to alter the frame of Government, and establiſh the Lawes of
the Land, we ſhall need to give it no further anſwer then this. That
if to raiſe an Army in our juſt defence, when another is marching to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards
us, to deſtroy us and our lawes, be to alter the frame of
Government, then is that ARMY raiſed for that purpoſe,
otherwiſe it is for our owne, and the lawes neceſſary preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And not long after, the</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">Ex<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct Coll<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ct on p. 695. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> Lords and Commons <hi>in their</hi> Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstrance
<hi>Novemb. 2. 1642. in</hi> anſwer to his Majeſties Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration
the 26 of <hi>May</hi> 1642. concerning the Commiſſion of Array,
<hi>hath theſe notable Paſſages;</hi> But moſt injuriouſly, moſt maliciouſly it
is affirmed by the contrivers of this Anſwer, That we told the King
that we might without want of modeſty and duty depoſe him. Did we
ſo much as once name that word, the ſignification whereof we profeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed,
that we did not ſuffer it ſo much as to enter into our thoughts?
Did we ſay, that with duty and modoſty we might depoſe the King,
becauſe we ſaid, we never ſuffered it to enter into our thoughts?
Or doe not they rather ſay it, that will needs make Preſidents to be
rules and patternes? Sure when we ſaid, That ſome Preſidents
were ſuch, as that they ought not to be rules for us to follow, we
might by any ingenious Reader, with much more probability beene
thought to have intended thoſe of depoſing Kings, then to have ſaid
that with duty and modeſty Kings might be diſpoſed, becauſe we affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med
that we had not ſuffered ſuch things to enter into our
thoughts.</p>
            <p>And although they would perſwade his Majeſty that there is little
confidence to be placed in our Modeſty and duty, yet as God is witnes
of our thoughts, ſo ſhall our actions witneſſe to all the world, that to
the honour of our Religion, and of thoſe that are moſt zealous in it,
(ſo much ſtrucken at by the Contrivers of that Declaration under
odious names) we ſhall ſuffer more from and for our Soveraign, then
we hope God will ever permit the mallice of wicked Councellors to
put us to, and though the happines of this and all Kingdomes depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth
cheifly upon God, yet we acknowledge that it doth ſo mainly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend
upon his Maj. and the Royall Branches of that Root, That as we
have heretofore<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo we ſhall hereafter esteem no hazard too great, no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
reproach too vile, but that we shall willingly go through the one, and
undergo the other. That we and the whole Kingdome may enjoy that
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:115470:7"/>
happineſſe, which we cannot in an orderly way of providence expect
from any other fountain or Streams, then thoſe from whence (were
the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>oyſon of evill counſels once removed from about them) wee
doubt not, but we and the whole Kingdom ſhould be ſatisfied moſt
abundantly.</p>
            <p>Therefore Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> the Barreſter as well as M. <hi>Prynne</hi> the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
and both Houſes of <hi>Parliament</hi> too, are point blanke againſt
the preſent arraigning, depoſing and executing of the King, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demning
it as a <hi>Popiſh</hi> and <hi>Ieſuiticall Practiſe,</hi> never owned, but
<hi>diſclaimed</hi> by every <hi>Proteſtant Parliament,</hi> and by this <hi>Parliament</hi>
in two expreſſe <hi>Declarations, two</hi> ſolemne <hi>Proteſtations,</hi> and in the
<hi>ſolemne League and Covenant</hi> ſince; all which this <hi>Pamphleter</hi>
tooke, and aſſented to, as readily as any other <hi>Members;</hi> and
therefore cannot excuſe himſelfe from moſt <hi>deteſtable prevaricati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi>
and <hi>perjury,</hi> in violating theſe his ſolemne <hi>Proteſtations. League
and Covenant,</hi> with his <hi>Oathes of Supreamacy and Allegiance</hi> to
boot, which he hath oft times taken, the guilt and infamy whereof
muſt reſt upon his conſcience, and eternally cry for vengeance a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt
him, unleſſe he expiate it by timely and deep repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <p>Fourthly, Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> the Barreſter in his Epiſtle to the Reader
before his fourth Part, thus expreſſeth himſelfe. <hi>For my own pa<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e
as I have <hi>alwayes been, and euer ſhall be</hi>
               </hi> an Honour, <hi>a Defender
of Kings and Monarchy,</hi> (the beſt of <hi>Government. whiles it
keeps within the bounds which law and conſcience have preſcribed)
ſo I ſhall never ſo far degenerate below the duty of a man, a Lawy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,
a Scholler, a Chriſtian,</hi> as to miſinforme or flatter either, nor
yet (out of any popular vaine-glory) court either Parliaments or
people to the prejudice of KINGS IVST ROYALTIES, but carry
ſuch an equall hand between them, as ſhall doe right to both, Inju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry
to neither, to preſerve, and ſupport their juſt and legall Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigntyes,
juriſdictions, Rights, within their proper limits without
tyrannicall invaſions, or ſeditions incroachments one upon another,
This is Mr: <hi>Prynne</hi> the Barreſters ſence.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>And in the third Part of his Soveraign Power of Parliaments and
Kingdomes: page 147. he concludes thus.</hi> Let Gods curſe and
mens for ever reſt upon all thoſe, who are in love with any warre,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:115470:8"/>
eſpecially a civill, within their own deareſt Countries bowells; <hi>Or
<hi>Dure abuſe my loyull ſyncere Lucubrations, to any diſloyall ſini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter
deſignes to the preiudice of their Soveraignes,</hi>
               </hi> or the States
wherein they live; which he never publiſhed, to countenance or encou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage
any tumultuous, <hi>REBELLIOUS</hi> factions, ambitions, <hi>Trayterous
Spirits,</hi> to mutiny or <hi>Rebell againſt their Soveraigns:</hi> but only out
of a cordiall deſire to effect ſuch a ſpeedy, honourable, ſafe, religious,
ſempeternall Peace between <hi>King and Parliament,</hi> as all true Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian
Engliſh hearts, both cordially pray, long for, &amp; endeavour. Ergo
<hi>Mr.</hi> Prynne <hi>the Member, and Barreſter, is ſtill one and the ſame man,
an aſſertor of</hi> Monarchy <hi>and</hi> Loyalty, <hi>and no wayes contradictory
to himſelfe in any of his writings; and</hi> Gods curſe <hi>and</hi> mans <hi>muſt reſt
upon this</hi> unpurified Pamphleter, <hi>for his malicious perverting of his
words, againſt their ſcope and purpoſe, to juſtifie the</hi> depoſing <hi>and
murthering of the</hi> King; <hi>and altering of our</hi> Monarchy.</p>
            <p>5ly. Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> the Barreſter, neither in his 4. <hi>Part of the Sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne
Power of Parliaments,</hi> nor in his <hi>Appendix</hi> to them, hath
produced any one <hi>Preſident</hi> (no not of any one <hi>Popiſh Parliament</hi>
or <hi>Kingdome)</hi> that ever judicially condemned or executed their law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<hi>King,</hi> were he never ſo <hi>Tyrannicall, impious</hi> or <hi>flagitious;</hi> much
leſſe any <hi>Proteſtant Parliament</hi> or <hi>Realme,</hi> who condemne and ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hor
both the <hi>Doctrine and Practiſe of murthering or deſtroying
their Kings,</hi> as <hi>Jeſuiticall, Papall, impious, Heriticall and damnable;
abjured by the very Oath of Allegiance;</hi> as he proves expreſly. <hi>Part.</hi>
1. p. 1. 2. 3. 4. Therefore Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> the Member, in his <hi>Memento,</hi> is
of the ſelfe ſame Judgement, as he was in his <hi>Soveraigne power of
Parliaments:</hi> in both which this <hi>Pamphleter</hi> (a <hi>Member of the high
Court of Iuſtice,</hi> who condemned the King to death) may read his
<hi>Neck-Verſe,</hi> and fatall <hi>deſtiny</hi> if he repent not.</p>
            <p>All other Paſſages truly quoted out of Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> the Barreſter, to
prove the <hi>Soveraigne Power of Parliaments and Kingdoms,</hi> (not of
a Peece of a Parliament, or Kingdome, much leſſe of a ninth part of a
Commons Houſe ſitting under a force, who are neither a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
nor Kingdome) Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> the Member ſtill averres, in this and
his owne <hi>genuine ſence,</hi> as they are printed in his <hi>Books,</hi> not as they
are mangled, and miſapplied by this idle <hi>Scribler,</hi> to thoſe few
Commons now ſitting, <hi>p.</hi> 5. 6. &amp;c,</p>
            <p>2dly Whereas he alleageth <hi>p.</hi> 7. 8. 9. 10. That <hi>William Prynne</hi> the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:115470:8"/>
Member his <hi>first Argument againſt the Iunto</hi> is: <hi>That their pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceedings
againſt the King is an Offence within the Statute of</hi> 25. E.
3. <hi>concerning Treaſon. I William Prynne the Barreſter doe remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,
that in the beginning of this late Warre the Cavaliers uſed the
ſame Argument againſt the Parliaments raiſing Armes, and I then
made this Anſwer to it,</hi> p. 107. <hi>of my ſaid firſt Part:</hi> That <hi>The Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament
and Whole Kingdome, being the Higheſt Power, cannot
by any publike Acts or Votes of theirs conſented to in Parliament be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come
Traytors or guilty of High Treaſon againſt the King, either by
the Common Law, or the Statute of 25. E. 3. c.</hi> 2. of Treaſons; <hi>which
extends, not to <hi>the whole Kingdom, or Court of Parliament</hi> repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting
it (of which no Treaſon was ever yet preſumed)</hi> &amp;c. <hi>William
Prynne</hi> the Barreſter and Member is ſtill of the ſame opinion, and
not repugnant to him ſelfe; who ſpeaks there, of a WHOLE KING<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>DOME,
AND COVRT OF PARLIAMENT (as this
<note n="*" place="margin">Page. 5 6 8 9.</note> 
               <hi>Pamphletter</hi> relates his words, and the Titles of all his 4. Parts
manifeſt) conſiſting of <hi>Lords and Commons,</hi> and that in a condition of
<hi>freedom and ſafety,</hi> ſitting in a <hi>full and free Parliament:</hi> But he
never meant nor intended it, of the <hi>Houſe of Commons</hi> alone, acting
and voting without and againſt the <hi>Houſe of Lords;</hi> nor of a Houſe
of <hi>Commons</hi> ſitting &amp; acting under a horrid <hi>Arme<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> force,</hi> as now much
leſſe of a <hi>remnant of a Commons-Houſe</hi> ſitting and Voting when
near nine parts or ten of their <hi>fellow-members</hi> are by a mutinous
Army impriſoned, ſecluded and driven away from the <hi>Houſe:</hi> or of
40. or 50 <hi>Commons</hi> ſitting under a force and uſurping to themſelves
without and againſt the conſent of their ſecluded <hi>Fellow Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers,</hi>
the <hi>ſupreame Authority of the Kingdom, making Acts of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament,</hi>
and erecting a New <hi>High Court of Juſtice</hi> without
the <hi>Lords</hi> or their <hi>Fellow Nembers</hi> conſents, to indite, ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne,
condemne and execute the <hi>King</hi> as a <hi>Traytor,</hi> and without
the whole Kingdomes, or <hi>Scotlands</hi> and <hi>Irelands</hi> joynt conſents, of
which he is likewiſe <hi>King.</hi> Such a Parliament, as this conſiſting of
ſome 50. or 60 Commons only without <hi>King, Lords,</hi> or the reſt
of their <hi>Fellow Commoners,</hi> he never heard nor read of in any age,
and ſo could never intend it: and therefore in his <hi>Memento,</hi> might
very well mind them of committing <hi>Treaſon,</hi> within this Law; what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever
they Vote, order, or ordain, or Enact in ſuch a thin <hi>Houſe</hi> under
a force, whiles the other Members are ſecluded, being by Mr. <hi>Speakers</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:115470:9"/>
owne <hi>Declaration</hi> of July 30. 1647. and the <hi>Ordinance of both Houſes</hi>
Auguſt 20. 1647. <hi>declared to be meerly null and void to all intents
even at the time of its Voting Ordering, Ordaining enacting, &amp; ever
after:</hi> and ſo no prea at all <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> juſtifie ſuch <hi>Members</hi> in the caſe they
be indicted, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d arraigned of <hi>High Treaſon</hi> for it.</p>
            <p>3 <hi>Whereas this</hi> Pamphletter, <hi>p. 11 ſuggeſteth. That</hi> Wil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Prynne
<hi>the Member in</hi> the rehearſal of the Statute of 25. E. 3. hath foulely
miſcarried and falſified the words of it <hi>(in his</hi> Mement<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>) <hi>For where
as the Statute mentions</hi> nothing at all touching <hi>depoſing the King;</hi>
he urgeth the Statute thus. That it is no leſſe then High Treaſon
for any man by overt act to compaſs or imagin the depoſition or death
of the King: Adding the word <hi>depoſition;</hi> which is no where found
in the whole Statute.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>To this Mr.</hi> Prynne <hi>the Member anſwers. 1. That this</hi> Ignoramus,
<hi>hath foulely miſ-recited and falſifyed his words, by omitting part of
them: which are theſe. Firſt,</hi> I ſhall minde them, that by the
<hi>Common Law</hi> of the Realme, <hi>(which he omits)</hi> the Statute <hi>of</hi> 25.
E. 3. <hi>and all</hi> other Acts concerning Treaſons <hi>(omitted likewiſe
by this</hi> Scribler) it is no leſſe than High-Treaſon for any man, by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert
Act to compaſſe or imagine the depoſition or death of the King:
<hi>quoting</hi> Cook <hi>and</hi> Stamford <hi>in the margin: and 21. R</hi> 2. Plac. Cor.
<hi>num. 4. 6. 7. in the Text.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now though the word <hi>depoſing,</hi> be not in the <hi>Statute</hi> of 25. E. 3.
yet it is in the <hi>Lawbooks</hi> which he cites, and in the <hi>Parliament Roll</hi>
of 21. <hi>R.</hi> 2. which this <hi>Dulman</hi> never read.</p>
            <p>Therefore this abſurd obſervation and cenſure of his might well
have been ſpared. Secondly <hi>To compaſſe the depoſing (or impriſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning)
of the King is in expreſſe Words</hi> declared to <hi>be Treaſon</hi> by the
Statutes of 26 H. 8. c. 13. 1. E. 6. c. 12. 1. <hi>Eliz</hi> c. 6. 13. <hi>E.</hi> c. 1.
and is no leſſe then High Treaſon within the meaning and intention
of 25 E 3; c. 2. though not within the Letter, as our<note n="*" place="margin">Cook 3. inſtit. ch. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> p. 5. 6. 12 13. and 7. Rep. 10, 11</note> 
               <hi>Law-books</hi>
and all the Judges of <hi>England</hi> have reſolved. Therefore Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi>
the Member ſtands <hi>rectus in Curia,</hi> againſt this ignorant falſe aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
            <p>4ly, What Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> the Barreſter writ concerning the <hi>Oath of
Supremacy,</hi> quoted p. 11 12: he doth ſtill averre as to the firſt
branch of it, (which is diſtinct from the latter) as applyed to the
<hi>whole Parliament,</hi> not to the Houſe of <hi>Commons</hi> alone, or thoſe <hi>few
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:115470:9"/>
Members</hi> now ſitting in it, under a force; of which he never inten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
that paſſage, to whom it is here miſapplyed: Only he muſt in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form;
this <hi>Gentleman;</hi> that the latter clauſe of this Oath; <hi>And do pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe
that from henceforth, I ſhall bear true allegiance to the Kings
<hi>Highne, his</hi> heirs and lawful ſucceſsors; <hi>and to my power ſhall aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſt
and defend all Iuriſdictions, Priviledges, and Preheminences
granted or belonging to the Kings Highneſſe, his Heirs and Suc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſors
on, united and anexed to the Imperiall Crowne of this Realme:
So help me God.</hi>
               </hi> &amp;c. Is a diſtinct clauſe from the former; which hee
and his Confederates in their late proceedings have quite forgotten:
and ſhall one day anſwer for ſuch wilfull <hi>perjury,</hi> in this or the world
to come, if they repent not of it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>5thly. Whereas he addes p.</hi> 13. That the Oath of Allegiance re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lates
only to the Popes unlawfull exerciſe of Authority and Iuriſdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction
within the Kingdome: <hi>And that</hi> William Prynne <hi>the Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber
in his</hi> rehearſall makes the Oath to run thus.</p>
            <q>That the Pope neither of himſelfe, nor by any Authority of the
Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> or by any other means, nor any other hath power,
&amp;c. and ſo inſtead of the words with any other, implying the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority
of the Pope joyned with others, he makes it a diſtinct clauſe,
nor any other, and ſo upon this forgery including the Parliament
within thoſe words, nor any other, he would make this proceeding
againſt the King to be contrary to the Oath of Allegiance.</q>
            <p>Mr. <hi>Prynn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi> the Member anſwers; Firſt, that though this <hi>Oath doth
principally</hi> relate to the <hi>Popes unlawfull</hi> exerciſe of Authority and
Jurisdiction within this Realme; yet it relates not only and ſolely to
it, as he pretends. The whole ſcope of this Oath is; <hi>To ſecure our
Kings from being depoſed, or murdered by their Subjects, or any other:</hi>
The greateſt danger the Parliament then feared, as to thoſe two
<hi>Treaſons</hi> and <hi>Miſchiefs,</hi> was principally from the <hi>Pope</hi> and his <hi>Popiſh
Inſtruments,</hi> who maintained and averred, <hi>the lawfullneſſe of de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſing
and murthering Christian Princes excommunicated or de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prived
by the Pope, by their Subjects, or any other.</hi> Againſt which
miſchife this <hi>Oath</hi> and Statute principally provides; it being contrary
to the Doctrine and Practiſe of all Proteſtant Churches and Subjects.
But can any man argue. This Oath provides againſt the depoſing and
murthering of our Kings by the Pope or Popiſh Subjects or Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,
by any influence or authority from the Pope. <hi>Ergo</hi> it is law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:115470:10"/>
for Proteſtant Subjects and Parliaments to depoſe and murther
their Kings without infringing this Oath? Doth not that Law and
Oath which provides againſt the greateſt and moſt likelyeſt Aſſaſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nates
and Depoſers of our Kings provide likwiſe againſt the leſſer
and more unuſuall? and is not a Proteſtants depoſing and murthering
of his Prince as treaſonable, as unlawfull as a Papiſts, yea and farre
worſe in this reſpect, becauſe it hardens and juſtifies them therin, ſcan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dalizeth
and croſſeth the very practiſe and principles of the prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
Religion? If ſo, then both are alike within the intent and mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning
of this Law and Oath, though the Pope and his inſtruments be
pincipally intended.</p>
            <p>2dly. Theſe clauſes in the Oath: That the Pope neither by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
nor with <hi>any other</hi> hath any <hi>power or authority to depoſe the
King</hi> &amp;c. <hi>That I will bear true Allegiance to his Maieſty, his
Heirs and Succeſſors, and him and them will defend to the utter moſt
of my power, <hi>againſt all attempts whatſoever,</hi>
               </hi> (a univerſall affir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mative
from or by the Pope or any others) <hi>which ſhall be made a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst
his or their perſons, their Crown, and Dignity, by reaſon or
colour of any ſuch ſentence or Declaration, <hi>or otherwiſe:</hi>
               </hi> Which
laſt words in the diſ-junctive coupled with the former generall ones:
and compared with the following clauſe: <hi>And that neither the Pope
<hi>nor any perſon whatſoever,</hi> hath power to abſolve me from this Oath,
or any part thereof</hi> &amp;c. and with the firſt branch of it. <hi>I do truly and
ſincerely acknowledge, profeſſe, teſtify, and declare in my Conſcience,
before God and the world, that our Soveraigne Lord King</hi> Charles,
<hi>is lawfull and rightful King of this Realme, <hi>and of all his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſties
Dominions and Countries:</hi>
               </hi> with this addition, that <hi>all Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant
Subjects are enjoyned to take this Oath,</hi> as well as <hi>Papiſts,</hi> and
<hi>more</hi> eſpecially every <hi>member of the Commons houſe of Parl.</hi> without
taking whereof he is utterly diſabled to be a <hi>Member,</hi> Doe infalliby
evidence, that this Law and Oaths related not <hi>only,</hi> though <hi>princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pally,</hi>
to the Popes Uſurpations in this Realm, but to all other Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects
uſurpations to depoſe or murther the King by any uſurped or
pretended Authority, or High Court of Juſtice whatſoever.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>But that which clears it unanſwerably is this; That this very</hi> Act
<hi>provides, That</hi> every Gentleman or perſon of higher degree, or any
perſon or perſons, which hath born or ſhall bear any Office or place of
Captain, Leiutenant, or any other place, charge or Office in Camp ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my,
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:115470:10"/>
or Company of Soldiers, or Conducters of Soldiers, shall goe or
paſſe voluntarily out of this Realme, to ſerve any forreign Prince,
State, or Potentate <hi>(be it Proteſtant or Popiſh,)</hi> before that he shall
become bound by obligation with two ſuch ſuertyes as shall be alowed
of by the Officers therein limited to take the ſame Bond, <hi>unto our
Sovereign Lord the Kings Majeſty, HIS HEIRES and SUCCESS<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>R;
in the ſum of <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>wenty pounds of</hi> currant Engliſh money at the leaſt,
with condition to the effect following, shall be a Felon. The Tenour
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>f which condition followeth: <hi>viz.</hi> That if the within bounden shal
not at any time thereafter be reconciled to the Pope, or Sea of <hi>Rome,
<hi>nor</hi>
               </hi> Shall enter into or conſent unto <hi>any practiſe, plot or conſpiracy
whatſoever againſt the Kings maieſty his heirs and Succeſsors:
or any of his or their</hi> Eſtate or Eſtates, <hi>Realmes</hi> or <hi>Dominions:</hi>
but shall within convenient time after knowledg thereof had, reveal
and diſcloſe to <hi>the Kings maieſty his heirs and Succeſſors,</hi> or ſome
of the Lords of <hi>his</hi> or <hi>their</hi> Honourable Privy Councell
<hi>all ſuch practiſes, plots and conſpiracyes,</hi> that then the ſaid Obligati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
be voyd. <hi>Which condition being generall, extending to</hi> any Plot,
practiſe or conſpiracy whatſoever, againſt the King, His Heirs and
Succeſſors or any of his or their Eſtate or eſtates, Realms or
Dominions; <hi>without any limitation to the Pope, or other ſorraigne
Prince, State or Potentate, or to popiſh Recuſants only; and reach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
as well to plots, practiſes and conſpiracies by any Subjects what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever,
as well within the Realme as without; be they proteſtants, pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt,
or whatſoever Sect or Religion: fully clears and proves the
Oath of</hi> Allegiance <hi>to extend though principally to the pope and
forraign Princes and States, and their Treaſons and Conſpiracies, yet
only unto them; but likewiſe to the Treaſons, Plots, Practiſes &amp; con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiracies
by any ſubjects whatſoever within the realm, &amp; to the preſert
diſloyal votes, acting &amp; <hi>Ieſuitical</hi> proceedings of the members now
ſitting.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, For the pretended perverting of the words of this oath
by Mr. <hi>Prynne,</hi> viz: <hi>Nor any other;</hi> for, <hi>nor with any other,</hi> It is but
the Printers overſight &amp; omiſſion, Nor doth it alter the ſence in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance,
For if the Pope cannot joining <hi>with any other,</hi> (ſuppoſe the
Members now ſitting in the Commons houſe or the high Court of
Iuſtice) lawfully depoſe nor murther the King, then certainly thoſe
<hi>Any other,</hi> cannot lawfully depoſe, nor murther him without the
Pope; within the true meaning of this Oath, under pain of deepeſt
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:115470:11"/>
perjury and Treaſon to boot: which I deſire this <hi>Pamphletter</hi> now
ſeriouſly to conſider, if he hath any honeſty or conſcience leſt
within him.</p>
            <p>6thly. What is objected out of <hi>Mr. Prynnes</hi> Appendix p. 14 is
already ſufficiently anſwered and cleared in the <hi>firſt and ſecond
ſection;</hi> and there is nothing in it, which can juſtifie the late triall,
arraignment and condemnation of the King in the leaſt degree,
triable by no law of God or man by ſuch an uſurped and illegall
Iuriſdiction, amounting to <hi>Tyranny</hi> in the ſuperlative Degree. And
for the condemnation and beheading of <hi>Mary Queen of Scotts;</hi> it
was not by her own Parliament and Subjects in her own Kingdom,
for any Treaſon againſt them; but for Treaſon committed in <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>land</hi>
againſt <hi>Queen Elizabeth,</hi> where ſhe was a Subject and no
Queen at all; and that by a ſurpriſe, as ſome relate.</p>
            <p>7thly. To that objected, p. 15 <hi>Touching the name and Title</hi>
which <hi>WILLIAM PRYNNE the Member is pleaſed to give
to the Parliament</hi> (he meanes the 45 Commons; who are no Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament)
<hi>now ſitting, calling it,</hi> A preſent unparliamentary Iunto.
I <hi>William Prynne</hi> the Barreſter <hi>do call to mind, that when the King
and divers of the Lords and Commons in the beginning of our late
Troubles had deſerted the Parliament, I did then in my ſaid firſt</hi>
Part of the Soveraigne Power of Parliaments p: 43, 44 <hi>maintaine
and prove;</hi> That the remaining part was a Parliament, notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
the perſonall abſence of the reſt; and that, as long as thoſe
abſent are Members of the Parliament, they ſhall ſtill be legally
preſent, whether they will or no.</p>
            <p>To this Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> the Member anſwers. Firſt, That what he
hath written as a <hi>Barreſter</hi> in theſe two Pages of his <hi>Firſt Part,</hi>
will prove fatall to this <hi>Pamphletter</hi> and his <hi>Junto</hi> now ſitting, if
well conſidered, and truly recited. For firſt, he there proves;
<hi>That there can be no Parliament without the King, who ought to be
alwayes perſonally preſent, in or neare his Parliament:</hi> which he
hath more fully manifeſted as a <hi>Barreſter,</hi> in his <hi>Plea for the Lords,</hi>
p. 7. to 13. by many Authorities and Records. The 45. Commons
therefore now ſitting without the <hi>Lords</hi> and their <hi>Fellow Members</hi>
concurrence, and againſt their <hi>Votes,</hi> having <hi>illegally</hi> and
<hi>trayterouſly</hi> condemned the <hi>King to looſe his Head;</hi> and act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
as an intire Parliament, without the King, Lords or their
Fellow Members, can be no Parliament at all, but a meer <hi>unpar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liamentary
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:115470:11"/>
J<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>nto,</hi> by <hi>Mr. Prynne</hi> the <hi>Barreſters</hi> Reſolution, to
which this <hi>Scribler</hi> refers. And ſo much the rather, becauſe they
will quite diſſolve this Parliament, by putting the King to death.
For the Parliament being but the <hi>Kings Parliament and great
Councell,</hi> and an <hi>Authority</hi> not an <hi>Intereſt,</hi> originally called and
authoriſed to ſit by the Kings Writ alone, which abates and expires
by his death; and enables not to conſult without, but only <hi>with the
King</hi> of buſineſſes concerning <hi>The King and His</hi> Kingdome; as
theſe clauſes of the Writ import. <hi>Carolus</hi> &amp;c. <hi>cum NOS de ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſemento
et conſenſu Conſillij NOSTRI pro quibuſdam arduis et
urgentibus negotijs NOS, Statum &amp; defenſionem Regni NOSTRI
ANGLIAE concernent: quoddam PARLIAMENTVM NOS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TRVM</hi>
&amp;c. <hi>tenere ordinavimus: Et ibidem vobiſcum</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Regni
NOSTRI COLLOQVIVM HABERE</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Quod perſonali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter
interſitis NOBISCVM</hi> &amp;c. <hi>ſuper DICTIS NEGOTIIS tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctaiur.
Et ad faciendum et conſentiendum his quaenunc et. ibidem, de
Communi Conſilio dicti Regni NOSTRI contegerit ordinari ſuper
NEGOTIIS ANTEDICTIS</hi> &amp;c. The King therefore being
put to death, the Parliament muſt of neceſſity be diſſolved by it,
ſince it can be no more his Parliament, his Councell, nor conferre
with HIM about HIS and HIS Kingdomes affaires for which
they were called, and elected to treat of as the Peoples Attorneys
or Truſtees: the King being both the <hi>Head, the beginning, end
and foundation of the Parliament</hi> (which cannot ſubſiſt without
him, no more then a naturall body without an head, or an houſe
without a foundation) as our<note n="*" place="margin">Modus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Parliamen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tum Cook 4. I<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſtit. c. p. 1. 2. &amp;c. Cromp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tons Iuriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction of Courts. f. 1. 2. So my Ple<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> for L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ds p. 7. to 12.</note> 
               <hi>Law books</hi> reſolve: and ſo was it
expreſly adjudged and agreed 1. H. 4. <hi>rot. Parl. n.</hi> 1. 14. H. 4. Cook 4.
<hi>Inſtit.</hi> p. 46. &amp; 4. E. 44. 44. <hi>b. That by the death of the King the
Parliament is ipſo facto diſſolved,</hi> as all other Courts held only by
his <hi>Writ or Commiſſion</hi> are. Neither will the Act made this Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
in the 17. year of this King, <hi>To prevent Inconveniences which
may happen by the untimely adjourning, Proroguing or Diſſolving of
this preſent Parliament,</hi> which enacted: <hi>That this PRESENT
PARLIAMENT now aſſembled ſhall not be DISOLVED, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogued,
or adjourned unleſſe it be by Act of Parliament to be paſſed
for that purpoſe:</hi> continue this Parliament in being after the Kings
death, for theſe reaſons. Firſt, becauſe the ſcope &amp; intent of this Act
(made before our late Warres) was only to diſable the King to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>journe
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:115470:12"/>
prorogue, or diſſolve this Parl. by any Proclamation or Royall
Act of his, without the conſent of both houſes; as the very title, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logue
and cloſe of it reſolve: But never to continue it ſtill a Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
in caſe of the King death, againſt which it never intended to
provide, it being a legall and abſolute diſſolution of it by the very
fundamentall conſtitution of Parliaments, and the Common Law of
the Realme.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Becauſe the King is the head and principall
Member of this preſent Parliament; and the firſt perſon in the enact<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
Parl. Be it declared and enacted BY THE KING &amp;c. and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
when he ceaſeth to be and is cut off, the Parliament muſt of ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
ceſſity ceaſe to be, as well as if the Lords and Commons had all bin
dead or murdered by the Army, in which caſe the Parliament had bin
ended notwithſtanding this Act, which cannot make a thing in being
which is actually deſtroyed, no more then a dead man to be alive,
Becauſe it was never the intention of the King, Lords and Commons
who were all parties to this act, to ſet up a new kinde of Parliament
without either King or Lords, or the <hi>Majority of the Commons houſe</hi>
or to veſt the Name, power and authority of the Parliament in an
eight or ninth part of the Commons houſe alone, (as now) when the
King, Lords and reſidue of the Commons were cut off and forced a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way
by the Armies violence.</p>
            <p>Such a thought as this never once entred into their heads. There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
the murthering of the King, the laying aſide the Lords houſe,
&amp; ſecluding of moſt of the Commons, muſt of neceſſity diſſolve this
preſent <hi>Parliament</hi> notwithſtanding this Act, as Maſter <hi>Prynne</hi> the
<hi>Barreſter,</hi> proved long ſince, before he was a <hi>Member,</hi> in his <hi>Plea,
for the Lords.</hi> p. 14 15. and ſo much the rather, becauſe without
them, no Act of Parliament can poſsibly be made this <hi>Parliament,</hi> to
diſſolve it, within the words or meaning of this Act. The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons
therefore now ſitting, having by their late exorbitant procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dings
and cutting off the Kings and Lords too in Mr. <hi>Prynne</hi> the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſters
judgement diſolved this preſent Parliament, and thereby con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently
diſſolved all Parliament Comittees in City and countrey,
together with all Ordinances of Parliament, and all<note n="*" place="margin">Cook 7. Rep. f. 29. 30. 31. Dyer 165. 4. E. 4. 44. 1. E. 5. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. a. 1. H. 7. 2 1. E. 3. 6, 7.</note> 
               <hi>Commiſſions,</hi>
of the <hi>Commiſsioners of the Great Seale, Iudges</hi> of the <hi>Kings
Courts, Iustices</hi> of the <hi>Peace, Sheriffes, and the like,</hi> and the <hi>Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ralls</hi>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:115470:12"/>
and all other Officers of the Armies Commiſsions likewiſe,
and put the Kingdome and Army into a miſerable confuſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</p>
            <p>Maſter <hi>Prynne</hi> the <hi>Member</hi> conceives he could then and now
give them, no other Title, but that, in his <hi>Memento,</hi> which he fears
the preſent age and poſterity will have juſt cauſe to give them, for
the miſeries they have brought, and are like to bring upon them<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
by their Vn-parliamentary and violent proceedings, which he doubts
wil end in their own ruine.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Maſter <hi>Prynne</hi> the <hi>Barrester</hi> in thoſe very Pages
proves,</p>
            <p>That not <hi>only the KING,</hi> but all the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons
ought to be preſent at the Parliament, and fined if they abſent
themſelves without juſt cauſe; and that all things ought to be
acted in Parliament by the Kings, Lords and Commons joynt
concurrence; only he addes,</hi> That <hi>if any of the Lords or Commons
when ſummoned, ſhall wilfully abſent themſelves, that the reſt may
ſit and proceed without them, <hi>and by the Kings conſent</hi> make whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome
Lawes for the Common wealth.</hi> But he neither there nor any
where elſe affirmed that the Lords and Commons could make bin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding
Lawes or Ordinances of Parliament without the King; or that
the Commons alone could make Acts of Parliament without the
Lords; as a few of them now they preſume; or that the eight or ninth
part only of the commons houſe ſitting under a force, when the reſt
of the Members are impriſoned, ſecluded and driven away thence by
the Armyes violence, were a <hi>compleat Parliament,</hi> or Houſe of <hi>com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons</hi>
to vote, order or act any thing (except only to adjourne, and
take Order to remove the force) or that what they voted or acted
under a force, was valid and binding to their fellow MEMBERS,
or any others: but he expreſſely affirmes the contrary: <hi>that whate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver
is voted or enacted whiles the Parl is under a force is void &amp;</hi>
null Part: 2. p. 86: <hi>And that no proceedings ought to be in Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
when moſt of the Members are abſent or driven away from it.</hi>
Part. 2. p. 7: which he proves more largely whiles a <hi>Barreſter</hi> and be
fore he was a <hi>Member;</hi> In his <hi>Levellers Levelled: and his Plea
for the Lords.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Therefore this <hi>Pamphletter</hi> hath much abuſed <hi>Maſter
Prynne</hi> in this his miſquotation and miſapplication of his words</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:115470:13"/>
3dly. <hi>Mr. Prynne</hi> the <hi>Barreſter</hi> in the <hi>firſt part</hi> of his <hi>Soveraigne
power of Parliaments,</hi> which this <hi>Scribler</hi> quotes p. 28. cites and cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures,
the unwarrantable Practiſe of King <hi>Richard the</hi> 2d (for which
he was <hi>articled againſt in the Parliament of</hi> 1H. 4. when he was
depoſed<note n="*" place="margin">Gr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>fton p 329. Mr. Saint Iohns Speech. 1640. p: 33. 1. H4 n 21. 22. 48.</note>) That in <hi>the 21 years of his Reigne, he unduly packed a
Parliament, and by his extradordinary armed Guard of</hi> 4000: <hi>Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhire
Archers over-awed and forced it to Repeal the Parliaments of</hi>
10 &amp;. 11 Ri<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h. 2. and to attaint and condemne the <hi>Duke of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſter,
Earle of Warwick,</hi> and <hi>Earle of Arundell</hi> (then likewiſe
executed) <hi>of High Treaſon:</hi> After which <hi>adjourning the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment
to Shrewsbury,</hi>
               <note n="*" place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 2<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. R. 2. c. 12. 16. 1. H. 4. c. 3. Walſing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham Hiſt. Angliae p. 394. Gra<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ton Holinſhed</note> 
               <hi>he there ſubtilly procured an Act to paſſe by
common conſent. That the power of the Parliament ſhould remaine
in ſome few perſons, who (AFTER THE PARLIAMENT
DISSOLVED) ſhould determine certaine petitions delivered, but
not anſwered therein. By colour whereof, theſe Committees procee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
to other things generally touching the Parliament, and that by the
Kings appointment <hi>in derogation of the ſtate of the Parliament,
and diſcommodity and pe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nicious example of the whole Realme.</hi>
And by colour and authority thereof, he cauſed the Parliament Rolls
to be altered, againſt the effect of the foreſaid grant For which cauſe
the ſaid Parliament and all Acts and proceedings therein were nulled
and declared void in</hi> 1. H. 4. c. 2. 3. This very preſident <hi>Mr-Prynne</hi>
the <hi>Member</hi> cites in his <hi>Memento,</hi> p. 9<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 10. as the neareſt p<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>tterne
he could meet with, parallell to the preſent <hi>ſitting Iunto.</hi> Who
without any Act of Parliament, being not above the 9th. or 10th.
part at moſt of the Commons Houſe, and ſitting under an Armed
force, have taken upon them, not only the name and power of the
<hi>whole Parliament,</hi> to alter, null, <hi>repeal Votes, Orders and Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces
made in a full and free Houſe, Vote out their fellow Members,
and lay aſide the Lords Houſe,</hi> but likewiſe preſumed to repeal
old, <hi>and make new Acts of Parliament,</hi> to erect a new <hi>High
Court of Iuſtice</hi> to try, condemne and execute the King himſelfe
without any witneſſes legally and publikely produced againſt
him; to adjourn and put off the <hi>Terme</hi> it <hi>ſelfe</hi> to the great ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction
and delay of <hi>Juſtice,</hi> to order a new <hi>Great Seale of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi>
to be made without the <hi>Kings Effigies</hi> or <hi>Motto:</hi> to alter all
the ancient <hi>Writs, formes and proceedings at the Common Law in the
Kings name and Stile,</hi> to enact <hi>Commiſſions of Judges, Sheriffs
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:115470:13"/>
and Juſtices of Peace and the like to continue after the Kings death,</hi>
which are abſolutely<note n="*" place="margin">Cook 7. Rep. 30. 31. Dyer 165. a.</note> 
               <hi>null and expired</hi> by it: to enact and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claine
it to be <hi>High Treaſon</hi> for any man to proclaime <hi>Prince
Charles, King of England</hi> after his <hi>Fathers</hi> death (who is King of
<hi>England, Scotland, France</hi> and <hi>Ireland</hi> immediatly after his <hi>Fathers
execution,</hi> as is adjudged <hi>by all the Judges of England</hi> in <hi>Calums</hi> caſe
Cook 7. f. 10. 11. and Cook 3. Inſtit. p. 7. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ac. ch. 1.) though bound
thereto by the <hi>Common Law, the Oathes of Supremacy and Allegi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance,
the ſolemne League and Covenant,</hi> and the Statute of 1.
<hi>Jacobi</hi> ch. 1. Wherein the <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> in full <hi>Parliament
where <hi>All the whoſe body of the Realme and every Particular
Member thereof,</hi> were either by perſon or repreſentative by the
Lawes of the Realme deemed <hi>to be preſent,</hi>
               </hi> did <hi>with all poſſible
publike joy and acclamation, as <hi>A memoriall ſo all poſterities,</hi>
               </hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong
<hi>the Records of the High Court of Parliament <hi>for ever to
endure of their Loyalty, obedience and hearty and humble <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </hi>
publiſh, declare and ENACT;</hi> That they being <hi>boun<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>en there un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
both by the laws of God and Man <hi>did recognize and acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge;
that the Imperiall Crowne of the Realme of England, and
of all the Kingdomes, Dominions and Rights belonging to the
ſame, did immediatly</hi> by inherent birth-right, and lawfull and
undoubted Succeſſion diſcend and come to his <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>oſt excellent Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty
<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> 
                  <hi>being</hi> Lineally, Juſtly and lawfully ne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t and  ſole Heire
of the blood Royall of this Realme. <hi>And that by the goodneſſe of
Almighty God and</hi> lawfull right of Diſcent, <hi>his Majeſty was of
the Realmes and Kingdomes</hi> of England, Scotland France and
Ireland <hi>the moſt mighty and potent</hi> King: and thereunto they
did moſt humbly and faithfully ſubmit,</hi>
               <note place="margin">NOTE.</note> 
               <hi>and oblige themſelves,
their News and Poſterities for ever, until the laſt drop of their
bloods be ſpent: <hi>Beſeeching his Maj<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſty to accept of the ſame, as
the firſt fruits in that High Court of Parliament, of</hi> their loyalty
and faith to his Maieſty and his royal progeny and poſterity for
ever. <hi>And to</hi>
               </hi> Vote and declare <hi>High Treaſon,</hi> to be no <hi>Treaſon;</hi>
and <hi>Loyalty</hi> and <hi>Allegiance</hi> it ſelfe, to be <hi>High Treaſon</hi>
(contrary to all rules of Law, Juſtice, Honeſty, Religion, Reaſon,
Conſcience and<note n="*" place="margin">1. H. 4. c. 10 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. 6. c. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1 Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>iae c. 1. Cook. 3. Inſt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t. p. 2. 21. 22. 23.</note> 
               <hi>expreſſe Acts of Parliament)</hi> to terrifie and
ſcare poore <hi>ignorant people</hi> from their <hi>Loyalty</hi> and <hi>duties:</hi> when
as all wiſe men admire, decide, ſcorne ſuch pittifull exorbitant <hi>Bulls</hi>
and <hi>Bugbeares;</hi> which will affright themſelves moſt at laſt when
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:115470:14"/>
               <hi>Scelera, ſceleribus <gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>enda, Licentia ſcelerum eſt quae regna inviſa
tuetur;</hi> and armed violence be grown out of date; as they will (no
doubt) ere long. And then this <hi>Iuncto,</hi> will wiſh with all their ſouls
(but over late) they had harkned better to Mr. <hi>Prynnes</hi> timely <hi>M<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mento,</hi>
which will then riſe up in judgement againſt them, and this
<hi>Pamphletter,</hi> to condemne and leave them without the leaſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe.</p>
            <p>Upon the whole matter then, it will appear to all the world. That
Mr. <hi>Prynne,</hi> both as a <hi>Barreſter</hi> and <hi>Member</hi> is <hi>ſemper idem,</hi> and
no <hi>Changling, turn-coat,</hi> or <hi>Apoſtate</hi> from his firſt principles and
<hi>Engagements,</hi> as this perjured <hi>Pamphetter</hi> is; to whom he wiſheth
more <hi>Grace, Truth, Honeſty,</hi> and leſſe <hi>Deceit, Falſhood</hi> and <hi>Hypo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criſy
in his</hi> heart, and <hi>next Impreſſions,</hi> wherein he expects he will
anſwer the <hi>principal Conſiderations</hi> in his <hi>Memento,</hi> with the <hi>Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations,
Remonſtrances, Proteſtations, Petitions, Promiſes of both
Houſes, and the Solemn League and Covenant,</hi> therein recited, to
which he hath not in this <hi>Pamphlet</hi> attempted to return the laſt
ſhadow of an <hi>Anſwer,</hi> ſuch a worthy <hi>Champion</hi> hath he ſhewed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf,
and ſo unable to encounter his <hi>Antagoniſt,</hi> Mr. <hi>Prynne,</hi> either as
a <hi>Barreſter or Member</hi> of the <hi>Commons Houſe,</hi> Who having written
more then any man in def<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nce of the <hi>Soveraigne Power of Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments
and Kingdoms,</hi> conſidered only as they are <hi>rightly conſtituted
and qualified; is</hi> thereby engaged more then any man, to oppoſe
the <hi>abuſes extravagances, &amp; unparliamentary, diſloyall Proceedings,</hi>
of any, who ſhall preſume to wreſt, abuſe and pervert his <hi>Loyall Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thodox
writings</hi> contrary to his <hi>ſence</hi> and <hi>meaning</hi> to juſtifie their
<hi>unwarrantable, illegall, Tyrannicall</hi> and <hi>Treaſonable Actions,</hi> as this
<hi>Pamphletter,</hi> and ſome others of late have done.</p>
            <div type="postscript">
               <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
               <p>COl. <hi>P.</hi> is credibly reported, to be the Author of <hi>Prynne against
Prynne,</hi> by divers; yet others report, that his Sonne in Law Mr
<hi>Abb<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>t</hi> (a Member) is the <hi>Author,</hi> and the <hi>Col.</hi> only the ſurperviſer
of it at the preſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#TECH" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> however it is agreed by all that one of them is
the Author; and the Col. owning it at the preſſe, I muſt repute him
the Father of this ſpurious birth.</p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:115470:14"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
